<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xml:space="preserve" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" 
xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" 
xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 https://raw.githubusercontent.com/kermitt2/grobid/master/grobid-home/schemas/xsd/Grobid.xsd"
 xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">
	<teiHeader xml:lang="en">
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title level="a" type="main">Cheap talk, efficiency and egalitarian cost sharing in joint projects</title>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
				<availability status="unknown"><p>Copyright Elsevier BV</p>
				</availability>
				<date type="published" when="2006-11-09">9 November 2006</date>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<biblStruct>
					<analytic>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Murali</forename><surname>Agastya</surname></persName>
							<email>m.agastya@econ.usyd.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">SEPS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>H04 Merewether Building</addrLine>
									<postCode>2006</postCode>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Flavio</forename><surname>Menezes</surname></persName>
							<email>f.menezes@uq.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff1">
								<orgName type="department">School of Economics</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Queensland</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>St Lucia Qld</addrLine>
									<postCode>4072</postCode>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<author>
							<persName><forename type="first">Kunal</forename><surname>Sengupta</surname></persName>
							<email>k.sengupta@econ.usyd.edu.au</email>
							<affiliation key="aff0">
								<orgName type="department">SEPS</orgName>
								<orgName type="institution">The University of Sydney</orgName>
								<address>
									<addrLine>H04 Merewether Building</addrLine>
									<postCode>2006</postCode>
									<settlement>Sydney</settlement>
									<region>NSW</region>
									<country key="AU">Australia</country>
								</address>
							</affiliation>
						</author>
						<title level="a" type="main">Cheap talk, efficiency and egalitarian cost sharing in joint projects</title>
					</analytic>
					<monogr>
						<title level="j" type="main">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
						<title level="j" type="abbrev">Games and Economic Behavior</title>
						<idno type="ISSN">0899-8256</idno>
						<imprint>
							<publisher>Elsevier BV</publisher>
							<biblScope unit="volume">60</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
							<biblScope unit="page" from="1" to="19"/>
							<date type="published" when="2006-11-09">9 November 2006</date>
						</imprint>
					</monogr>
					<idno type="MD5">4DBD1F5377E488DEC85EBE638D451538</idno>
					<idno type="DOI">10.1016/j.geb.2006.09.005</idno>
					<note type="submission">Received 19 November 2004</note>
				</biblStruct>
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<appInfo>
				<application version="0.7.2" ident="GROBID" when="2023-02-22T11:29+0000">
					<desc>GROBID - A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</desc>
					<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid"/>
				</application>
			</appInfo>
		</encodingDesc>
		<profileDesc>
			<textClass>
				<keywords>
					<term>JEL classification: H410</term>
					<term>C72</term>
					<term>D830 Voluntary contribution mechanism</term>
					<term>Incomplete information</term>
					<term>Cheap talk</term>
					<term>Simple equilibria</term>
				</keywords>
			</textClass>
			<abstract>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Rarely, if ever, do parties contemplating a joint project commit resources without engaging in nonbinding discussions about who does what.</s><s>To examine the role of such discussions, we model the investment decision as a voluntary contribution game where each player is privately informed of her benefit from project's completion.</s><s>Efficiency of every equilibrium of this game is improved when a prior stage of communication is allowed.</s><s>Interestingly, this improvement can be achieved in "simple equilibria" where a player simply announces whether (not how much) she plans to contribute.</s></p><p><s>With symmetric priors, the simple equilibrium that maximizes either utilitarian ex ante welfare or the probability of completion has a curiously egalitarian feature-whenever the project is completed, each party contributes exactly half the cost, independent of private information.</s></p></div>
			</abstract>
		</profileDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<body>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="1.">Introduction</head><p><s>Rarely, if ever, do parties contemplating a joint project commit resources without engaging in non-binding discussions on who does what.</s><s>As one might expect, such discussions are more prominent when contemplating large undertakings where no one member has an incentive to complete the project on her own and spending her own resources without some assurance from the others would be too risky.</s><s>For instance, the International Thermonuclear Energy Reactor (ITER) program to demonstrate the scientific and technological feasibility of fusion energy began as an initiative between the US and Russia as early as 1985.</s><s>It took over three years before formal collaboration began.</s><s>Serious negotiations for a site for the reactor to reduce the cost of implementation of the program did not take place until 2003.</s><s>Similarly, the USCAR, a consortium representing a joint research venture between the Big Three auto makers did not take shape until 1992, although the initiative goes back to the period following the Cooperative Research <ref type="bibr">Act (1984)</ref> by the US Congress. 1  In this paper, we model the investment choices of two players who seek to undertake a joint project as a voluntary contributions game familiar from the literature on the private provision of discrete public goods.</s><s>The two players simultaneously choose how much to invest in the project, with the knowledge that any investment is foregone even if the project is not completed.</s><s>The project is completed only if the sum of their investments is at least the fixed (and commonly known) cost k.</s><s>The incremental benefit from a project's completion to a player is however her private information.</s><s>Our focus throughout is on situations where no one player has an incentive to complete the project on her own.</s><s>Section 2 contains a fairly complete analysis of this game.</s><s>Proposition 4 presents a simple necessary and sufficient condition for a positive (equilibrium) probability of the project's completion when the priors have interval supports.</s><s>The condition itself captures the intuition that for the completion of the project, the sum of interim benefits of the lowest types of the two players that might contribute a positive amount must cover the cost of the project.</s><s>Proposition 6 uses this to show that for concave priors in particular, either there is an equilibrium in which the project is completed with probability one or the project is never completed.</s><s>We view this exhaustive analysis of the contribution game as adding to a large literature on the private provision of public goods using a voluntary contribution scheme. 2 It also sets the stage to study the implications of cheap talk.</s></p><p><s>In Section 3, we augment a prior stage of communication to the above game.</s><s>The communication scheme we consider is very simple-players simultaneously communicate only whether they plan to make a contribution ("y") or not ("n").</s><s>Further, we restrict attention to "simple equilibria".</s><s>In a simple equilibrium, denoted by S(x), there is a threshold x.</s><s>Player 1 and Player 2 first announce y only if their respective values for the project are at least x and k − x.</s><s>Unanimous announcements of y are followed up by a contribution of x by Player 1 and k − x by Player 2 and the project is completed.</s><s>Otherwise no contributions are made.</s></p><p><s>Proposition 15 shows that every equilibrium of the contribution game is Pareto dominated in an interim and an ex ante sense by some simple equilibrium despite its coarse revelation of information.</s><s>Instead of the Pareto criterion, if a scalar welfare measure is used to rank equilibria, such as the ex ante probability of the project's completion or the players' aggregate welfare, then all the equilibria of the contribution game can be uniformly dominated by a single simple equilibrium.</s><s>(See Propositions 11 and 16.) Furthermore, if types are identically distributed according to a regular distribution, it turns out that the most efficient simple equilibrium (according to the 1 See http://www.ofes.fusion.doe.gov/iter.html</s><s>and http://www.uscar.org/uscar/history.htm</s><s>for information on ITER project and USCAR respectively.</s></p><p><s>2 An exception is <ref type="bibr" target="#b3">Menezes et al. (2001)</ref> which studies other mechanisms besides the contribution mechanism.</s><s>They do not consider the role of cheap talk.</s><s>Regardless, for the two-player contribution game, our informational assumptions are more general and the results sharper.</s></p><p><s>utilitarian social choice rule or the probability of completion), is the one where both parties share the cost equally.</s><s>The "best" equilibrium in this case is curiously egalitarian.</s><s>An intuition for why communication results in superior outcomes can be gained by entertaining, for the moment, the existence of an equilibrium of the original game of the following kind: Player 1 (Player 2) of a type above a threshold v1 ( v2 ) contributes an amount x (k − x) and other types do not contribute.</s><s>The project is completed only in the states (v 1 , v 2 ) such that v 1 v1 and v 2 v2 .</s><s>The total contribution from the marginal types is k.</s><s>Therefore, the total expected benefit of these types must be as high as k and since no one player completes the project on her own, v1 + v2 &gt; k.</s><s>On the other hand, in the simple equilibrium S( v2 ), the project is completed in the additional states (v 1 , v 2 ) such that k − v2 v 1 v1 and v 2 v2 .</s><s>This leads to an increased probability of completion in an ex post efficient region and results in superior efficiency.</s><s>The key ingredient in the above argument is that the marginal valuations that make a positive contribution sum to greater than k.</s><s>Lemma 7 establishes this property for arbitrary equilibria of the contribution game and lies at the heart of the efficiency results we obtain.</s></p><p><s>Although the focus of the paper is on how limited communication can help, in Section 4.2 we show that any ex ante efficient mechanism among those that satisfy IC and ex post IR can be implemented as full communication equilibria if players announce their types.</s><s>Remaining subsections of Section 4 discuss other aspects of our work.</s></p><p><s>This paper studies the implications of adding a non-binding communication stage to an economic game.</s><s>Other such contributions include <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Crawford and Sobel (1982)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Farrell and Gibbons (1989)</ref>, <ref type="bibr">Forges (1990)</ref>, <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baliga and</ref><ref type="bibr">Sjostrom (2003), Doraszelski et al. (2003)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Matthews and Postlewaite (1989)</ref>.</s><s>The reader is directed to <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Farrell and Rabin (1996)</ref> or <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baliga and Morris (2002)</ref> and the references therein for a further discussion of the role of unmediated communication.</s></p><p><s>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b2">Farrell and Gibbons (1989)</ref> and <ref type="bibr">Matthews and Postlewaite (1989)</ref> the underlying economic game is a bilateral trade of a private good through a κ-double auction.</s><s>Whereas we demonstrate that communication is always welfare enhancing for the contribution game, it is not necessarily so for the double auction.</s><s>This is clear since it is known that, albeit under special assumptions on the priors, the ex ante efficient payoff frontier among all bilateral trading mechanisms that satisfy IC and ex post IR can be implemented through equilibria of κ-double auctions for varying values of κ (see <ref type="bibr" target="#b5">Satterthwaite and Williams, 1989)</ref>.</s><s>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b0">Baliga and Sjostrom (2003)</ref>, unlike here, the ex post efficient outcome is independent of players' types.</s><s>In <ref type="bibr" target="#b1">Doraszelski et al. (2003)</ref>, the ex post efficient outcomes depend on aggregate uncertainty which imply correlated utilities.</s></p><p><s>To summarize, the contribution game is unique in that allowing exchange of binary messages is enough for greater efficiency despite the fact that it has a continuum of types and actions.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="2.">The contribution game</head><p><s>A joint project between two partners requires a total investment of k &gt; 0 to complete.</s><s>The players simultaneously choose how much to contribute.</s><s>For i = 1, 2, if Player i contributes an amount c i , her payoff is v i − c i if c 1 + c 2 k (i.e. the project is completed) and −c i otherwise.</s><s>The benefit v i is Player i's private information while the other maintains a prior that it is a random draw from a continuous distribution F i whose support is an interval</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_0">[v i , v i ]. Let C(F 1 , F 2 ) denote the induced Bayesian game. A typical equilibrium of this game is a tuple (C 1 , C 2 ) where C i : [v i , v i ] −→ R.</formula><p><s>Two notable assumptions are implicit in the above description of the environment.</s><s>First, the values of the players are independently distributed.</s><s>This is an important restriction.</s><s>Correlation between types warrants a separate analysis.</s><s>Second, the benefit from not undertaking the project is normalized to zero.</s><s>Therefore v i is the minimum incremental benefit of Player i from completing the project.</s><s>We assume that this is non-negative.</s><s>Also assume that v 1 + v 2 &gt; k to ensure that there are some valuations for which it is ex post efficient to complete the project.</s></p><p><s>A more substantive restriction is our focus throughout to situations where no player has an incentive to complete the project on her own.</s><s>Accordingly</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_1">vi &lt; k for i = 1, 2<label>( 1 )</label></formula><p><s>is maintained throughout the paper.</s></p><p><s>(1) makes each player pivotal for the project.</s><s>It is then immediate that neither player making a contribution regardless of her type is always an equilibrium.</s><s>The question of interest is whether there are equilibria in which the project is completed with a positive probability.</s><s>To address this issue, first define a "cost sharing" equilibrium as follows.</s></p><p><s>Definition 1 (Cost Sharing Equilibrium).</s><s>An equilibrium (C 1 , C 2 ) is said to be a cost sharing equilibrium if for i = 1, 2,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_2">C i (v i ) = x i if v i vi , 0 otherwise for some non-negative x i such that x 1 + x 2 = k and for some vi ∈ [v i , v i ).</formula><p><s>In a cost sharing equilibrium a player contributes a constant x i if and only if her type is above a given threshold vi .</s><s>With vi &lt; k and x 1 + x 2 = k, in a cost sharing equilibrium the project is completed with a positive probability.</s><s>Lemma 2 below presents a simple necessary and sufficient condition for the existence of a cost sharing equilibrium.</s><s>Proposition 4 then shows that the same condition applies to arbitrary equilibria.</s><s>Define</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_3">H (v 1 , v 2 ) = 1 − F 2 (v 2 ) v 1 + 1 − F 1 (v 1 ) v 2 . Lemma 2. C(F 1 , F 2 ) admits a cost sharing equilibrium if and only if there exists vi ∈ [v i , v i ) such that H ( v1 , v2 ) k.</formula><p><s>(2)</s></p><p><s>(2) is intuitive.</s><s>Observe that (1 − F j ( vj )) vi is the expected benefit of the marginal type vi should a cost sharing equilibrium exist.</s><s>Therefore, H ( v1 , v2 ) is merely the total expected benefit of the two marginal types in this equilibrium.</s><s>The condition in Lemma 2 then says that a cost sharing equilibrium exists if and only if there is a pair of marginal types whose total expected benefit is at least as high as the cost of completing the project.</s></p><p><s>Proof.</s><s>Suppose a cost sharing equilibrium exists with (v 1 , v 2 ) being the tuple of marginal types and (x 1 , x 2 ) the respective shares of the cost.</s><s>The expected payoff of type v i from contributing x i is (1 − F j (v j ))v i − x i .</s><s>Being the marginal type, she must weakly prefer contributing x i to not making a positive contribution, an action that results in a zero payoff.</s><s>H (v 1 , v 2 ) k is then merely the implication that the sum of these payoffs is non-negative.</s></p><p><s>Conversely, suppose (2) holds.</s><s>Assume without loss of generality 3 that the inequality is in fact binding for some (v 1 , v 2 ).</s><s>Then define x i = (1 − F j (v j ))v i and conclude that only types v i and above making a positive contribution of x i , for i = 1, 2, constitutes a cost sharing equilibrium.</s><s>2</s></p><p><s>The following notation is used at various places in the paper.</s><s>Given an equilibrium (C 1 , C 2 ) in which the project is completed with a positive probability, let c i and c i respectively denote the supremum and the infimum of all the positive contributions among all types of Player i.</s><s>Also let w i denote the infimum of all types of Player i that contribute a positive amount and w i the infimum of all types of Player i that choose c i .</s><s>As we point out in the proof of Proposition 4, we must have C i (v i ) = c i in any equilibrium.</s><s>Therefore w i is well-defined.</s><s>Without loss of generality, C i (•) is right continuous.</s><s>(See footnote 4.) Therefore c i = C i (w i ) &gt; 0.</s></p><p><s>Remark 3. The lowest positive contribution of one player and the highest contribution of the other must add up to the exact cost of the project.</s><s>That is,</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_4">c i + c j = k, i = j and i, j = 1, 2.</formula><p><s>(3)</s></p><p><s>(3) offers a testable hypothesis of equilibrium behavior.</s><s>To see why it must be true, first note that since Player j contributes at least c j , clearly c i k − c j .</s><s>Now suppose that the inequality is strict.</s><s>By definition of c j , there must exist a type v j such that C j (v j ) ∈ (c j , k − c i ).</s><s>Then, by construction, C j (v j ) + C i (v i ) &lt; k for all v i which means that the marginal probability of the project's completion conditional on Player 2 contributing C j (v j ) is zero.</s><s>Consequently, Player 2 is better off not to contribute at all than contributing C j (v j ) &gt; 0. This contradiction establishes (3).</s></p><p><s>Proposition 4. The project is completed with a positive probability in some equilibrium of</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_5">C(F 1 , F 2 ) if and only if there exists v i ∈ [v i , v i ) such that H (v 1 , v 2 ) k. Proof. If H (v 1 , v 2 ) k for some (v 1 , v 2 )</formula><p><s>, by Lemma 2 a cost sharing equilibrium exists and establishes the proposition.</s><s>To prove the converse, let (C 1 , C 2 ) be an equilibrium in which the project is completed with a positive probability.</s><s>We will show that H (w 1 , w 2 ) k.</s></p><p><s>For well known reasons of incentive compatibility, C i (•) is necessarily non-decreasing.</s><s>Consequently, there is no loss of generality in assuming that C i (•) is also right continuous. 4 The contribution c 1 is thus made by Player 1 of types in the interval</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_6">[w 1 , v 1 ]. By Remark 1, with a contribution of c 1 , c 1 + C 2 ( ṽ2 ) k if and only if ṽ2 w 2 . Therefore, the equilibrium payoff of type w 1 is 1 − F 2 (w 2 ) w 1 − c 1 . (4a)</formula><p><s>Since c 1 is the highest contribution of Player 1, it then follows that the probability that the project is completed when Player 2 contributes c 2 is exactly (1 − F 1 (w 1 )) and hence the equilibrium payoff of type w 2 is</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_7">1 − F 1 (w 1 ) w 2 − (k − c 1 ). (<label>4b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_8">)</formula><p><s>4 Let v i be an arbitrary point of discontinuity of</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_9">C i (•) such that C i (v i ) &lt; lim v↓v i C i (v) = c * .</formula><p><s>Given that the types are continuously distributed, type v i must be indifferent between contributing c * and C i (v i ).</s><s>Now let Ĉi (•) be the function that differs from C i (•) only at points of discontinuity such as v i and define Ĉ(v i ) = c * described above.</s><s>Since a monotonic function on a compact interval can have only countably many discontinuities, it follows that ( Ĉ1 , Ĉ2 ) is also an equilibrium.</s><s>Therefore ( Ĉ1 , Ĉ2 ) induces the same set of equilibrium outcomes as (C 1 , C 2 ), except over a set with measure zero.</s></p><p><s>Noting that the expressions (4a) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_7">4b</ref>) must be non-negative and summing them yields H (w 1 , w 2 ) k. <ref type="formula">2</ref>Remark 5.</s><s>With concave priors, it is possible to obtain a much simpler condition for which Lemma 2 obtains.</s><s>Note that (2) really is of interest only when</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_10">v 1 + v 2 &lt; k.</formula><p><s>(5)</s></p><p><s>For, if v 1 + v 2 k, it is always ex post efficient to complete the project.</s><s>When that is true, for Player 1 to contribute v 1 and Player 2 to contribute k − v 1 constitutes an equilibrium in which the project is completed with probability one, regardless of any further assumptions on the prior distributions.</s><s>Interestingly, the converse also holds with concave priors.</s><s>Proposition 6. Suppose F i (•) is concave for i = 1, 2 and (5) holds.</s><s>Then, in the unique equilibrium of the contribution game, each player makes a zero contribution.</s><s>The project is never completed.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_11">Proof. Since F i (•) is concave, H (•,•) is convex in each of its arguments. Thus the maxi- mum value of H (•,•) is achieved at one of the four corners namely (v 1 , v 2 ), (v 1 , v 2 ), (v 1 , v 2 ) and (v 1 , v 2 ). The respective values of H (•,•) at these points are v 1 + v 2 , v 2 , v 1 and 0. Thus H (v 1 , v 2 ) &lt; k for all (v 1 , v 2 ).</formula><p><s>Apply Proposition 4 to complete the proof. 2</s></p><p><s>We end this section with one further property of equilibria of C(F 1 , F 2 ).</s><s>Like (3), the inequality in the following lemma offers another testable hypothesis of equilibrium behavior.</s><s>Equally important is the role it plays in establishing the results in Section 3.</s></p><p><s>Lemma 7. w 1 + w 2 &gt; k in any equilibrium of C(F 1 , F 2 ) in which the project is completed with a positive probability.</s></p><p><s>Proof.</s><s>Let (C 1 , C 2 ) be an equilibrium in which the project is completed with a positive probability.</s><s>Let q i = (1 − F j (w j )) and p i = (1 − F j (w j )).</s><s>Without loss of generality let q 2 q 1 .</s><s>Since the project is completed with a positive probability, using (1) and Remark 3, q 2 &gt; 0. By individual rationality for type w i , we have q i w i c i and hence q 2 (w 1 + w 2 ) c 1 + c 2 .</s><s>Moreover, to satisfy the incentives of type v 2 we have <ref type="formula" target="#formula_1">1</ref>) and q 2 p 2 , then substitute k for v 2 on the RHS of this inequality to note that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_12">p 2 v 2 − c 2 q 2 v 2 − c 2 . Substitute c 2 = k − c 1 from Remark 3 to get c 1 + c 2 (q 2 − p 2 )v 2 + k. Use (</formula><formula xml:id="formula_13">c 1 + c 2 q 2 (1 + (1 − p 2 )/q 2 )k.</formula><p><s>Using the upper and lower bounds for c 1 + c 2 in the above paragraph, we obtain that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_14">w 1 + w 2 (1 + (1 − p 2 )/q 2 )k &gt; k. 2</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.">Cheap talk</head><p><s>We now turn to implications of adding a prior stage of non-binding communication to C(F 1 , F 2 ).</s><s>Each player is assigned a binary message space M = {y, n} where y stands for the announcement "Yes, I will make a contribution" and n stands for "No, I will not contribute" to the project's cost.</s><s>Having observed their types, players simultaneously and publicly announce y or n.</s><s>This is followed by a play of the contribution mechanism of the previous section.</s><s>Let C * (F 1 , F 2 ) denote the induced multistage game with observed actions.</s><s>By an equilibrium of C * (F 1 , F 2 ), we mean a Perfect Bayesian Equilibrium (PBE). <ref type="foot" target="#foot_1">5</ref></s><s>t is worth reiterating that our interest here is not in the entire gamut of outcomes that can be achieved through an equilibrium of some cheap talk extension of C(F 1 , F 2 ).</s><s>See Section 4.2 in this regard.</s><s>Rather, the idea here is to demonstrate that even limited communication of two messages can increase efficiency despite the fact that C(F 1 , F 2 ) involves a continuum of types and actions.</s><s>What is more, such an increase can be achieved in equilibria of C * (F 1 , F 2 ) that have the following simple structure.</s><s>Let S(x) denote a simple strategy profile in which Player 1 contributes x.</s><s>We shall say that an equilibrium of C * (F 1 , F 2 ) is a simple equilibrium if it involves a simple strategy profile.</s><s>We will use the same notation S(x) to denote any simple equilibrium in which the corresponding simple strategy is played.</s><s>The following Lemma settles the question of existence of simple equilibria.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_15">Definition 8 (Simple Strategy Profile of C * (F 1 , F 2 )). A strategy profile in C * (F 1 , F 2 ) is</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 9. S(x) is a simple equilibrium if and only if</head><formula xml:id="formula_16">x ∈ [k − v 2 , v 1 ]. Proof. See Appendix A. 2</formula><p><s>Remark 10.</s><s>As discussed earlier, when (5) is violated, the project can be completed with probability one even without cheap talk.</s><s>To keep the role of cheap talk interesting, we assume ( <ref type="formula">5</ref>) in what follows.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.1.">Cheap talk and probability of completion</head><p><s>To see that cheap talk can sometimes help, it is enough to consider C(F 1 , F 2 ) when the priors are concave.</s><s>Absent communication, by Proposition 6, the unique equilibrium is for neither player to contribute.</s><s>In contrast, in any simple equilibrium S(x), the project is completed whenever v 1 x and v 2 k − x, and hence with the positive probability</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_17">(1 − F 1 (x))(1 − F 2 (k − x)) for any x ∈ (k − v 2 , v 1 ).</formula><p><s>Interestingly, the next result shows that such an increase in probability of completion extends to arbitrary priors.</s><s>Let</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_18">x p ∈ arg max x∈[k−v 2 ,v 1 ] 1 − F 1 (x) 1 − F 2 (k − x) .</formula><p><s>(6) S(x p ) is a simple equilibrium under which the project is completed with the highest probability compared to all other simple equilibria of the cheap talk game C * (F 1 , F 2 ).</s></p><p><s>Proposition 11.</s><s>The project is completed with a greater probability in the simple equilibrium S(x p ) of the cheap talk game than in any equilibrium of the contribution game without cheap talk.</s></p><p><s>Proof of the above proposition relies on Lemma 7. Due to (1), this lemma implies that the project is not completed unless Player i's type is at least w i , for both i = 1, 2. In contrast, in the simple equilibrium, S(w 2 ), the project is completed for additional realizations v = (v 1 , v 2 ) when k − w 2 v 1 w 1 and v 2 w 2 .</s><s>This essentially constitutes the proof of Proposition 11.</s></p><p><s>Proof.</s><s>The project is completed with probability</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_19">(1 − F 1 (x p ))(1 − F 2 (k − x p )</formula><p><s>) in the equilibrium S(x p ).</s><s>In an equilibrium (C 1 , C 2 ) of the game without cheap talk, the probability that the project is completed is no more than (1 − F 1 (w 1 ))(1 − F 2 (w 2 )).</s><s>By Lemma 7, we have w 2 &gt; k − w 1 and thus the probability of completion is less than</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_20">(1 − F 1 (w 1 ))(1 − F 2 (k − w 1 ))</formula><p><s>which in turn, by definition of x p , is no greater than probability of completion in the equilibrium S(x p ). 2 Remark 12. Recall that a probability distribution F is said to be regular if (1 − F (t))/f (t) is decreasing, where f is the density of F .</s><s>If types are i.i.d according to a regular F , it may be verified that x p = k/2.</s><s>In other words, for regular distributions, the simple strategy in which the costs are shared equally also maximizes the probability of completion of the project.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="3.2.">Cheap talk and efficiency</head><p><s>We now evaluate the superiority of simple equilibria in terms of their payoffs rather than the probability of completion.</s><s>The various notions of efficiency that we study are standard in the literature but are listed below for completeness.</s></p><p><s>Given an equilibrium E (of either</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_21">C(F 1 , F 2 ) or C * (F 1 , F 2 )) let U E i (v i ) denote the interim payoff of Player i of type v i with U E i = E[U E i (v i )]</formula><p><s>denoting her ex ante expected payoff.</s></p><p><s>Definition 13 (Interim Pareto Dominance).</s><s>An equilibrium E is said to interim Pareto dominate another equilibrium</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_22">Ê if U Ê i (v i ) U E i (v i ) for i = 1, 2 and for almost all v i ∈ [v i , v i ]</formula><p><s>with the inequality being strict for a generic subset of types of each player.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Definition 14 (Ex ante Pareto Dominance).</head><p><s>An equilibrium E is said to ex ante Pareto (strictly) dominate another equilibrium</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_23">Ê if U Ê i &gt; U E i for i = 1, 2.</formula><p><s>Observe that when comparing one equilibrium with another, we require that both players are made strictly better off.</s><s>It is easy to check that if an equilibrium E is interim Pareto dominated by another equilibrium Ê, then the latter also ex ante Pareto dominates E. The converse of course is not true in general.</s></p><p><s>Proposition 15.</s><s>For every equilibrium of the contribution game, there exists a simple equilibrium of the cheap talk game that dominates it in the interim-Pareto (and hence in the ex ante Pareto) sense.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proof. See Appendix A. 2</head><p><s>Again, Lemma 7 is the key ingredient to the proof Proposition 15.</s><s>Intuitively, as in the case of Proposition 11, the additional ex post efficient states in which the project is completed due to communication enhance efficiency.</s></p><p><s>It is important to note that the choice of the dominating simple strategy in the above proposition will usually depend on the particular equilibrium of C(F 1 , F 2 ) that one is seeking to dominate.</s><s>In general, it is not possible for any one simple equilibrium to uniformly dominate all the equilibria of the contribution game. <ref type="foot" target="#foot_2">6</ref></s><s>Uniform dominance is however possible if an aggregate welfare based on the ex ante utilities of the two players is used to rank equilibria.</s></p><p><s>Let φ : R × R −→ R be a social welfare function and</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_24">φ(U E 1 , U E 2 ) be the aggregate welfare in an equilibrium E of C(F 1 , F 2 ) or C * (F 1 , F 2 ).</formula><p><s>Proposition 16.</s><s>Suppose that welfare is measured according to a continuous function φ(•,•) that is strictly increasing in both its arguments.</s><s>Then, there exists x φ ∈ [k − v 2 , v 1 ], such that welfare in the simple equilibrium S(x φ ) is greater than the welfare in any equilibrium of the contribution game.</s></p><p><s>Proof.</s><s>Let E be an equilibrium of C(F 1 , F 2 ) and apply Proposition 15 to choose an equilibrium S(x) such that ex ante Pareto dominates E. Since φ(•,•) is increasing in both its arguments, φ(U</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_25">S(x) 1 , U S(x) 2 ) &gt; φ(U E 1 , U E 2 ). Choose x φ ∈ arg max x∈[k−v 2 ,v 1 ] φ(U S(x) 1 , U S(x)</formula><p><s>2</s></p><p><s>) to complete the proof. 2 A much stronger characterization obtains if one assumes that priors are regular (See Remark 12) and that the welfare criterion is utilitarian.</s><s>First define</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_26">ψ i (x) = 1 f i (x) v i x 1 − F i (t) dt i = 1, 2. (<label>7</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_27">)</formula><p><s>Proposition 17. Suppose welfare is measured according to the function φ(u 1 , u 2 ) = u 1 + u 2 .</s><s>Also, assume that F i is regular for i = 1, 2. x φ in Proposition 16 is the (unique) solution to the equation</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_28">ψ 1 (x) = ψ 2 (k − x). Moreover, if F 1 = F 2 then x φ = k/2.</formula><p><s>Proof.</s><s>See Appendix A. 2</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.">Discussion</head><p><s>In this section, we briefly discuss various aspects of our work.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.1.">Efficiency of simple equilibria</head><p><s>In Sections 3.1 and 3.2, we have shown that simple equilibria have attractive properties when compared to the equilibrium outcomes without communication.</s><s>Can simple equilibria in turn be dominated by other equilibria of C * (F 1 , F 2 )?</s><s>We do not have an answer to this question for general distribution functions.</s><s>The next result is the answer for a class of concave priors.</s></p><p><s>Let</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_29">x * i ≡ arg max x∈[k−v 2 ,v 1 ] U S(x) i</formula><p><s>. That is, among all simple equilibria, Player i's ex ante payoff is the highest in S(x * i ).</s></p><p><s>Proposition 18. Assume that F 1 , F 2 are both concave and Proof.</s><s>See Appendix A. 2</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_30">v i + v j k, i = j . An equilibrium of C * (F 1 , F 2 ) is interim efficient if</formula></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.2.">Inefficiency of simple equilibria</head><p><s>Our analysis thus far has focused on how even limited communication in the form of simple equilibria can enhance efficiency.</s><s>In this section, we shall briefly discuss efficient outcomes when one allows arbitrary communication schemes.</s><s>In particular, our analysis will also highlight the (in)efficiency of the simple equilibria in this more elaborate class.</s><s>Throughout, we shall restrict our analysis to the case where</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_31">F 1 = F 2 = F is the uniform distribution on [v, v].</formula><p><s>Recall from the revelation principle, that an arbitrary procedure for deciding how to undertake the project can be described by a direct mechanism, i.e. a tuple μ := {p(•), x 1 (•), x 2 (•)} where p(v) is the probability that the project is completed and x i (v) is the expected payment of Player i following the reports v = (v 1 , v 2 ).</s><s>Let M denote the set of all μ that satisfy incentive compatibility, interim individual rationality and ex ante budget balance. 7</s><s>Let P denote the subset of M that are ex ante efficient.</s></p><p><s>Let C * * denote the cheap talk extension of C(F, F ) where players first publicly report a type and, having observed the reports, play the contribution game.</s><s>The next result shows that every μ ∈ P can be achieved as a fully revealing equilibrium of C * * .</s></p><p><s>Given α &lt; v, let g(α) = 3k/2 − v − α and p α (•) be the rule according to which the project is completed (with probability one) only when (v 1 , v 2 ) lies above the line joining (α, v) and</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_32">(v, g(α)). That is, p α (v) = 1 if v 2 m α v 1 + c α and p α (v) = 0 otherwise, where m α = −(2v + α − 3/2k)/(v − α) and c α = v − m α α. Let a 1 = (2 + m a )/3, a 2 = −(1 + 2m α )/3m α and a 3 = (α − a 2 (v + c a ))/2 Proposition 19. Suppose v + v &lt; k and F 1 = F 2 = F is the uniform distribution on [v, v].</formula><p><s>(</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_33">) μ := {p(•), x 1 (•), x 2 (•)} ∈ P if and only if p(•) = p α (•) for some α ∈ [k − v, k/2]. (2) For each α ∈ [k − v, k/2], p α (•)<label>1</label></formula><p><s>is achieved in the following FCE of C * * : Players truthfully report their types at the communication stage.</s><s>At the contribution stage, Player 1 contributes</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_34">x 1 (v) = a 1 v 1 + a 2 v 2 + a 3 and Player 2 contributes x 2 (v) = k − x 1 (v) if the reports v = (v 1 , v 2 ) satisfy v 2 m a v 1 +</formula><formula xml:id="formula_35">(v) + x 2 (v) − p(v)k] 0.</formula><p><s>Several remarks are in order.</s><s>Denote by C * (M 1 , M 2 ) a cheap talk extension of C(F, F ) with arbitrary message spaces M 1 and M 2 .</s><s>An equilibrium of this game is a full-communication equilibrium (FCE) if the types are fully revealed at the communication stage.</s><s>Let M * denote the set of all μ that can be achieved as the FCE of C * (M 1 , M 2 ) for some M 1 , M 2 .</s><s>Since, following the announcement stage the types are fully revealed in any FCE, ex post IR and budget balance must hold, which in turn imply interim IR and interim budget balance.</s><s>Therefore, M * is a subset of M. The above proposition is therefore a complete characterization of all the efficient outcomes that can be obtained by adding an arbitrary communication stage to C(F, F ).</s><s>It is also noteworthy that complicated message spaces are not necessary-players need only communicate their types-to achieve efficiency.</s></p><p><s>Next, no simple strategy is ex ante efficient.</s><s>To see this, recall that under p α (•) the project is completed only when (v 1 , v 2 ) lies on or above the line joining (α, v) and (v, g( <ref type="formula">α</ref></s></p><formula xml:id="formula_36">+ v 2 = k except at (k − v, v) and (v, k − v).</formula><p><s>On the other hand, it is clear that in every simple equilibrium, the project is undertaken in some part of the shaded region that lies between the line v 1 + v 2 = k and C. Therefore, no simple equilibrium is ex ante efficient.</s></p><p><s>Finally, a comment on the assumption of uniform priors.</s><s>In order to prove Proposition 19, we rely on <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Williams (1987)</ref>.</s><s>It turns out that the programming problem for characterizing P is isomorphic to the one studied by <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Williams (1987)</ref> for characterizing incentive efficient mechanisms for bilateral trade.</s><s>Therefore, an analogue of part (1) of the proposition can in fact be stated for all regular priors.</s><s>However, part (2) requires an explicit construction of a FCE of some C * (M 1 , M 2 ).</s><s>This appears substantially intricate unless priors are uniform.</s><s>We leave this as an avenue for future research.</s><s>The assumption that v + v k (for uniform priors) is however only Fig. <ref type="figure">1</ref>.</s><s>Project is not completed in the shaded region in any ex ante efficient allocation.</s><s>In every simple equilibrium, the project is completed in some part of the shaded region.</s><s>a simplifying assumption to avoid a cumbersome analysis of several cases.</s><s>(The inefficiency of simple strategies discussed above remains valid.)</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.3.">One-sided communication</head><p><s>C * (F 1 , F 2 ) was presented in Section 3 largely with the intent of showing how a "simple" communication scheme and "simple" strategies of that scheme can dominate all equilibria of the original contribution game.</s><s>It is only reasonable to ask if there even simpler mechanisms that can lead to a similar result.</s><s>For example, is there a cheap talk extension in which only one player chooses from a binary message space and has equilibria with similar efficiency properties.</s><s>The following argument shows that in general, communication by both players is necessary.</s></p><p><s>Assume, without loss of generality, that it is Player 1 who first publicly reports y or n after which the contribution mechanism is played.</s><s>Assume that the priors are symmetric and concave on [0, 1] and that k &gt; 1.</s><s>For an arbitrary v * 1 ∈ [0, 1], consider an equilibrium strategy of Player 1 in which she announces y if and only if her valuation is at least v * .</s><s>Then following the cheap talk phase, when the contribution game is played at the node y, the lowest possible valuation of Player 1 according to the revised prior is v * 1 , while that of Player 2 continues to be 0. Since the sum of these valuations v * 1 &lt; k, it follows from Proposition 6 that neither player will make a positive contribution.</s><s>Likewise at the node following the announcement of n by Player 1.</s><s>Therefore, in the original game and this cheap talk extension with one sided communication, the project is never completed.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head n="4.4.">More than two players</head><p><s>Many (though not all) of our results have an analogue in the case of n players provided one assumes that no subset of n − 1 players have an incentive to complete the project.</s><s>While this is the condition (1) in the case of n = 2, it is substantially more stringent when n &gt; 2. A more complete study of the situation involving n players can be a subject of future research.</s><s>requires that neither player make a positive contribution.</s><s>To support this outcome, it is irrelevant as to how one assigns the posterior beliefs at these nodes.</s></p><p><s>Since</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_37">v 1 + v 2 &gt; k, it is immediate that x &lt; v 1 and k − x &lt; v 2 . Therefore, for every x ∈ [k − v 2 , v 1 ],</formula><p><s>the node (y, y) occurs with a positive probability under the strategy profile S(x).</s></p><p><s>The continuation game at this node is C( F1 , F2 ) where Fi is the truncation of F i to [x i , v i ],</s></p><p><s>x 1 = x and x 2 = k − x.</s><s>Take the posterior beliefs that is consistent with Bayes rule at this node.</s><s>Given her beliefs, and the restriction of S(x) to this game, Player i knows that Player j will contribute x j for sure.</s><s>Therefore it is clearly a best response for her to contribute x i as long as her valuation exceeds x i which is the specification in S(x).</s></p><p><s>It remains to check that there are no incentives to deviate at the initial announcement stage.</s><s>Consider Player 1.</s><s>We will show that type x of Player 1 is indifferent between sending the messages y and n.</s><s>Now sending the message n leads to a payoff of zero as the project is not undertaken nor any contributions are made by either player.</s><s>Upon sending the message y, if called upon to contribute a positive amount, her contribution is x, which again yields a zero payoff.</s><s>Clearly, then all types of Player 1 exceeding x will strictly prefer to send the message y while there is no benefit of a type less than x since in the continuation game, it will need too contribute at least x for the completion of the project.</s><s>Thus Player 1's announcement choice in the cheap talk game is optimal.</s><s>A similar argument establishes that Player 2's choice of y if her type exceeds k − x and n otherwise is optimal.</s></p><p><s>The requirement that x v 1 and k − x v 2 for S(x) to be an equilibrium is immediate as otherwise at least one of the players will be expected to contribute an amount greater than the valuation of the highest type. 2 Given an equilibrium E of either C(F 1 , F 2 ) or C * (F 1 , F 2 ), let q E i (v) be the marginal probability that the project is completed given that Player i is of type v.</s><s>The following lemma which is required in the proofs of several results is essentially due to <ref type="bibr" target="#b4">Myerson (1981)</ref> and is stated without proof.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Lemma 21. Let E be an equilibrium of either</head><formula xml:id="formula_38">C(F 1 , F 2 ), C * (F 1 , F 2 ). Given any vi ∈ [v i , v i ], the equilibrium payoff of type v i vi is given by U i (v i ) = U i ( vi ) + v i vi q E i (t) dt, for all v i ∈ [ vi , v i ].</formula><p><s>Proof.</s><s>Omitted. 2</s></p><p><s>Proof of Proposition 15.</s><s>Consider an equilibrium E of C(F 1 , F 2 ).</s><s>As the project cannot be completed with probability one, at least one player with the lowest possible valuation does not make a contribution.</s><s>Assume then, without loss of generality, that w 1 &gt; v 1 so that U E 1 (w 1 ) = 0. Noting that the marginal probability of completion of the project given any equilibrium contribution of Player 1 does not exceed (1 − F 2 (w 2 )), by applying Lemma 21 the interim payoffs of Player 1 must satisfy the following:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_39">U E 1 (v 1 ) = 0 i f v 1 ∈ [v 1 , w 1 ), (v 1 − w 1 )(1 − F 2 (w 2 )) if v 1 ∈ [w 1 , v 1 ].<label>(8a)</label></formula><p><s>Turning to Player 2, the payoff of type w 2 of Player 2 is</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_40">U E 2 (w 2 ) = (1 − F 1 (w 2 ))w 2 − c 2 which is zero if w 2 &gt; v 2 but can be positive if w 2 = v 2 .</formula><p><s>Again, by Lemma 21, the interim payoffs of Player 2 must satisfy the following:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_41">U E 2 (v 2 ) = 0 i f v 2 ∈ [v 2 , w 2 ), (1 − F 1 (w 2 ))w 2 − c 2 + (v 2 − w 2 )(1 − F 1 (w 1 )) if v 2 ∈ [w 2 , v 2 ].<label>(8b)</label></formula><p><s>From Lemma 7, we know that w 1 + w 2 &gt; k.</s><s>Therefore, k − v 2 &lt; w 1 &lt; v 1 and hence by Lemma 9, S(w 1 ) is a simple equilibrium.</s><s>Let a = max{k − w 1 , v 2 }.</s><s>The interim payoffs in this equilibrium can be computed directly and are as follows:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_42">U S(w 1 ) 1 (v 1 ) = 0 i f v 1 ∈ [v 1 , w 1 ), (v 1 − w 1 )(1 − F 2 (k − w 1 )) if v 1 ∈ [w 1 , v 1 ]; (9a) U S(w 1 ) 2 (v 2 ) = 0 i f v 2 ∈ [v 2 , a), (v 2 − (k − w 1 ))(1 − F 1 (w 1 )) if v 2 ∈ [a, v 2 ].<label>(9b)</label></formula><p><s>Since w 1 + w 2 &gt; k, comparing (8a) and (9a) it is immediate that all types of Player 1 in the region [w 1 , v 1 ] are better off under S(w 1 ) relative to E while its remaining types are no worse off.</s><s>Now comparing (8b) and (9b), the types of Player 2 in the region [v 2 , a) receive a zero payoff in both equilibria while those types between [a, w 2 ) are clearly better off under S(w 1 ) relative to E. We now claim that the types in [w 2 , v 2 ] are also better off under S(w 1 ).</s><s>Let v2 satisfy</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_43">(1 − F 1 (w 1 )) v2 = c 2 . Clearly v2 w 2 . Consider now v 2 ∈ [ v2 , v 2 ] the difference U S(w 1 ) (v 2 ) − U E (v 2 ) is at least 1 − F 1 (w 1 ) v 2 − (k − w 1 ) − 1 − F 1 (w 1 ) w 2 − c 2 − (v 2 − v2 ) 1 − F 1 (w 1 ) = 1 − F 1 (w 1 ) (w 1 + w 2 − k) − 1 − F 1 (w 1 ) v2 − c 2 = 1 − F 1 (w 1 ) (w 1 + w 2 − k).</formula><p><s>From Lemma 3, we know that w 1 + w 2 &gt; k and thus for all</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_44">v 2 ∈ [v 2 , v 2 ], U S(w 1 ) (v 2 ) − U E (v 2 ) 0.</formula><p><s>Thus, we have shown that for i = 1, 2, all the types of Player i in the region [w i , v i ] obtain a higher payoff under S(w 1 ) relative to E. Since w i &lt; v i , S(w 1 ) interim and ex ante dominates E. 2</s></p><p><s>The following lemma identifies certain properties of regular distributions which are used in the proofs of Propositions 17 and 18.</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_45">Lemma 22. Let G(t) = (1 − F (t))</formula><p><s>where F is a regular distribution on <ref type="bibr">[v, v]</ref>.</s><s>Then the following hold:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_46">v x G(t) dt &lt; G(x) 2 f (x) and −1 − f (x)G(x) f (x) 2 &lt; 0. (<label>10</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_47">)</formula><p><s>Moreover, the function ψ</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_48">(x) = 1 f (t) v</formula><p><s>x G(t) dt in decreasing in x.</s></p></div>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Proof.</head><p><s>By assumption, G(•)/f (•) is decreasing.</s><s>The second inequality in (10) must hold as its LHS is merely the derivative of G(x)/f (x).</s><s>The first inequality is an be obtained by first multiplying and dividing the integrand on its LHS by f (t) and using the fact that G(t)/f (t) is decreasing.</s><s>Finally, differentiate ψ(•) to get</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_49">ψ (x) = − G(x) f (x) − f (x) f (x) 2 v x G(t) dt &lt; G(x) f (x) −1 − f (x)G(x) f (x) 2 &lt; 0 by (10).</formula><p><s>Therefore, ψ(•) is decreasing. 2</s></p><p><s>Proof of Proposition 17.</s><s>The interim payoffs in the equilibrium S(x) are as follows:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_50">U S(x) 1 (v 1 ) = 0 i f v 1 x, (1 − F 2 (k − x))[v 1 − x] if v 1 x;</formula><p><s>(11)</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_51">U S(x) 2 (v 2 ) = 0 i f v 2 k − x, (1 − F 1 (x))[v 2 + x − k] if v 2 k − x. (<label>12</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_52">)</formula><p><s>Use the above expressions and take the expectation of the interim payoffs U S(x) i (•) and then apply integration by parts to obtain the following expressions for the ex ante payoff</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_53">W i (x) ≡ E[U S(x) i (v i )] W 1 (x) = G 2 (k − x) v 1 x G 1 (t) dt, W 2 (x) = G 1 (x) v 1 k−x G 2 (t) dt (<label>13</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_54">)</formula><p><s>in the equilibria S(x), where</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_55">G i (x) = (1 − F i (x)), for i = 1, 2. Let B(x) ≡ φ(U x 1 , U x 2 ) = W 1 (x) + W 2 (x). Differentiating B(•) and simplifying yields B (x) = f 2 (k − x)f 1 (x) ψ 1 (x) − ψ 2 (k − x) .</formula><p><s>Given the definition of ψ i (•), B (k −v 2 ) &gt; 0 and B (v 1 ) &lt; 0. From Lemma 22, ψ i (•) is a decreasing function provided F i (•) is a regular distribution.</s><s>Therefore B (•) decreases from a positive value at k − v 2 to a negative value at v 1 .</s><s>Therefore, there is an interior x * at which B (x * ) = 0 and is the maximum of B(•). 2 Proof of Proposition 18.</s><s>Let E be an equilibrium strategy profile and let x i v i be the cutoff such that Player i reports y if and only if her type v i x i .</s><s>Let Fi be the posterior of Player i when following an announcement n which is truncation of F i to [v i , x i ].</s><s>Let Fi be the posterior of Player i when following an announcement y which is truncation of F i to [x i , v i ].</s><s>Note that Fi and Fi are both concave given that F i is concave to begin with.</s><s>Proposition 6 applies in each continuation game following the announcements.</s><s>The rest of the proof uses this.</s></p><p><s>With the posteriors as above, the total benefit of the lowest possible types following announcement's (n, n), <ref type="bibr">(y, n), (n, y)</ref> and (y, y) are respectively v 1 + v 2 , x 1 + v 2 , v 1 + x 2 and x 1 + x 2 .</s><s>Given our hypotheses, in the first three cases the sum is less than k.</s><s>Therefore by Proposition 6, 0-equilibrium is the unique equilibrium and if at all the project is completed, it must be at the node (y, y).</s></p><p><s>If x 1 + x 2 &lt; k, the project cannot be completed at the (y, y) node either and the dominance of E by some simple equilibrium is immediate.</s><s>Assume then that x 1 + x 2 k.</s></p><p><s>Let q i (v i ) denote the probability that the project is completed conditional on the history being (y, y).</s><s>Then using well known results for incentive compatible mechanisms, we have</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_56">U E i (v i ) = ⎧ ⎪ ⎪ ⎨ ⎪ ⎪ ⎩ 0 i f v i x i , (1 − F j (x j )) v i x i q E i (t) dt if v i x i . (<label>14</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_57">)</formula><p><s>Now let x = x 1 and consider S(x 1 ).</s></p><p><s>An inspection of the formulas ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_56">14</ref>), ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_51">12</ref>) and ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_51">12</ref>) shows that U</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_58">S(x) i (v i ) U S i (v i ) for all types v i . The inequality is strict for the types v 2 ∈ [x 2 , k − x 1 ] whenever x 1 + x 2 &gt; k.</formula><p><s>Let us now turn to Pareto dominance of equilibria in terms of ex ante payoffs.</s><s>This must be a subset of the interim-efficient equilibria, which are the simple strategies.</s><s>Recall that for this part of the Proposition, we assume that (F 1 , F 2 ) are regular.</s><s>The ex ante payoffs in S(x) are given by the formulas in (13).</s></p><p><s>Let x * i be the maximum of</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_59">W i (•) in the region [k − v 2 , v 1 ].</formula><p><s>If we show that x * i is unique and that x 1 &lt; x 2 , it would then follow that only those S(x) for x ∈ [x * 1 , x * 2 ] are ex ante efficient.</s><s>Toward this end, first note that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_60">W 1 (x) = f 2 (k − x)G 1 (x) 1 G 1 (x) v 1 x G 1 (t) − G 2 (k − x) f 2 (k − x) . (<label>15</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_61">)</formula><p><s>The sign of W (x) depends on the difference between the two expressions in the square brackets.</s></p><p><s>The value of the second expression is zero when x = k − v 2 , and since F 2 is regular, it is increasing to the right of k − v 2 .</s><s>Differentiate the first term and use Eq. ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_46">10</ref>) note that the first term is decreasing in x.</s><s>Its value is positive at x = v 1 , which is to the left of k − v 2 (by admissibility) only falls to zero at x = v 1 , which is to the right of k − v 2 .</s><s>Therefore, these two have a unique intersection x * 1 .</s><s>To the left of x * 1 , W 1 is positive and to its right W 1 is negative.</s><s>Therefore x * 1 is the unique maximum of W 1 (•).</s><s>Similarly, W 2 (•) also has a unique maximum, x * 2 .</s><s>To prove that x * 1 &lt; x * 2 , use (10) to note that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_62">W 1 (x) &lt; f 2 (k − x)G 1 (x) G 1 (x) f 1 (x) − G 2 (k − x) f 2 (k − x) . (<label>16</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_63">) Now let x * denote the unique maximum of the expression G 2 (k − x)G 1 (x) when x lies in [k − v 2 , v 1 ].</formula><p><s>It may be verified that x * is well defined due to the fact that F 1 and F 2 are regular.</s><s>It may also be verified that whenever x &gt; x * , the expression in the square brackets of ( <ref type="formula" target="#formula_60">15</ref>) is negative.</s><s>Therefore whenever x x * , W 1 (x) &lt; x is negative, which implies that x * 1 &lt; x * .</s><s>A similar argument shows that x * 2 &gt; x * and hence x * 1 &lt; x * 2 . 2</s></p><p><s>Proof of Proposition 19.</s><s>Consider any μ ∈ M. Integrating by parts the expression for interim utility given in Lemma 21, we have the following well known expressions for U i , the ex ante utility and x i , the expected contribution ex ante:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_64">U i = E v 1 − F i (v i ) f i (v i ) p(v) + U i (v i ), (<label>17a</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_65">)</formula><formula xml:id="formula_66">x i = E v v i − 1 − F i (v i ) f i (v i ) p(v) − U 1 (v 1 ), (<label>17b</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_67">) q i ( vi ) q i (v i ) whenever vi v i . (17c) Let Γ (p) = E v v 1 − 1 − F 1 (v 1 ) f 1 (v 1 ) + v 2 − 1 − F 2 (v 2 ) f 2 (v 2 ) − k p(v) (18)</formula><p><s>and write the ex ante budget balance condition</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_68">x 1 + x 2 − E(p(v))k 0 as Γ (p) U 1 (v 1 ) + U 2 (v 2 ). (<label>19</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_69">)</formula><p><s>Since the interim utility must be non-decreasing in a player's type, interim individual rationality is implied by</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_70">U i (v 1 ) 0 for i = 1, 2. (<label>20</label></formula><formula xml:id="formula_71">)</formula><p><s>Given λ ∈ [0, 1], consider the programming problem P λ defined as:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_72">P λ := max q(v) λU 1 + (1 − λ)U 2 s.t. (i). Γ (p) U 1 (v 1 ) + U 2 (v 2 ), (ii). U i (v i ) 0 for i = 1, 2.</formula><p><s>Observe that U i involves the expectation of a term that is always non-negative.</s><s>Therefore, any solution of P λ , inequality (i) must be binding.</s><s>Consequently, P λ is isomorphic to the less constrained problem described in <ref type="bibr">Williams (1987, p. 160</ref>).</s><s>To see this, intuitively regard Player 1 as seller whose cost is v1 = k − v 1 .</s><s>With this change of variable, (18) can be rewritten as</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_73">Γ (p) = E ( v1 ,v 2 ) v 2 + F 2 (v 2 ) − 1 f 2 (v 2 ) − v1 − F1 ( v1 ) f ( v1 ) p(v)</formula><p><s>which is exactly Eq. (4) in <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Williams (1987)</ref>.</s><s>Continuing the analogy of a buyer and seller, the cost of the seller varies between, using the notation of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Williams (1987)</ref>, a 1 = k − v and b 1 = k − v while the buyer's value ranges between a 2 = v and b 2 = v.</s><s>Since a 1 a 2 and b 1 b 2 and F 1 , F 2 are regular, 9 Theorem 4 of <ref type="bibr" target="#b6">Williams (1987)</ref>, which is based entirely on solutions to P λ , applies.</s></p><p><s>Accordingly, an ex ante efficient allocation of M is given by a rule φ s,t where</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_74">φ s,t ( v1 , v 2 ) = ⎧ ⎨ ⎩ 1 if v1 + t F1 (v 1 ) f1 (v 1 ) v 2 − s (1 − F 2 (v 2 )) f 2 (v 2 ) , 0 otherwise<label>(21)</label></formula><p><s>for 0 s, t 1 and such that Γ (φ s,t ) = 0. Substituting for F1 and F 2 as the uniform distributions on [k − v, k − v] and [v, v] respectively in the above, it follows that an ex ante efficient allocation involves a p such that p(v) = 1 if v lies above a line ϕ(v 1 ) = mv 1 + c and Γ (p) = 0. Also note that φ s,t ( v1 , v 2 ) = 1 implies v1 v 2 .</s><s>The implied p(v) = 0 unless v is ex post efficient.</s><s>Letting x 0 and y 0 denote the points of intersection of the line ϕ(•) with v 2 = v and v 1 = v respectively, we note that k − v x 0 , y 0 &lt; v, since p(•) is ex post efficient.</s><s>Substituting for m = −(v − y 0 )/(v − x 0 ) and c = v − mx 0 , an explicit calculation 10 gives</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_75">Γ (p) = 1 12 (v − x 0 )(v − y 0 )(x 0 + y 0 + v − 3k/2).</formula><p><s>9 Recall F i is uniform and is hence regular. 10</s><s>An analogue of this calculation is done in the Example of <ref type="bibr">Williams (1987, p. 167)</ref> when both the values of both the buyer and seller are uniform on [0, 1].</s></p><p><s>Writing g(α) = 3k/2 − v − α, we note that the pairs (x 0 , y 0 ) = (α, g(α)) where α ∈ [k − v, k/2], are the solutions to the equation Γ (p) = 0.</s><s>This proves that every p ∈ P corresponds to p α (•) in which the project is undertaken if and only if v lies above the line joining <ref type="bibr">(α, v) and (v, g(α)</ref>).</s><s>This proves part (1).</s></p><p><s>To prove part (2), we begin by checking the optimality of players' responses at the contribution stage.</s><s>It is enough to check that at every node, the actions constitute a Nash equilibrium.</s><s>This is clear at nodes where no contributions are made since zero contributions, by (1), are always an equilibrium.</s></p><p><s>Consider then a node v such that v 2 m α v 1 +c α .</s><s>The payoff of Player 1 is v 1 −x 1 (v 1 , v 2 ).</s><s>We will now verify this is non-negative.</s><s>To see this, first note that m α ranges from −1/2 to −2 and therefore a 2 0 and a 1 0. Use the facts that v = m α α + c α (since (α, v) lies on the boundary line) and 2a 1 + a 2 m α = 1 to conclude the following sequence of (in)equalities:</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_76">v 1 − x 1 (v 1 , v 2 ) = (1 − a 1 )v 1 − a 2 v 2 − a 3 (1 − a 1 − a 2 m α )v 1 − a 2 c α − α/2 + (v + c α )/2 (22) (since v 2 m α v 1 + c α ) = a 1 v 1 − a 2 c α − α/2 + a 2 (m α α + 2c α )/2 = a 1 v 1 − (1 − m α a 2 )α/2 = a 1 (v 1 − α) 0.</formula><p><s>A similar calculation shows that v 2 − x 2 (v 1 , v 2 ) 0. Hence (x 1 (v 1 , v 2 ), x 2 (v 1 , v 2 )) constitutes a Nash equilibrium of the complete information contribution game at the node v.</s></p><p><s>It remains to check that the strategies are incentive compatible at the communication stage.</s><s>Note that the marginal probability of completion if Player 1 reports v 1 is q 1 (v 1 ) = (1 − F (m α v 1 + c α )) when v 1 α and q 1 (v 1 ) = 0 otherwise.</s><s>Likewise for Player 2, q 2 (v 2 ) = (1 − F ((v 2 − c α )/m α )) if v 2 g(α) and q 2 (v 2 ) = 0 otherwise.</s><s>Through a direct computation, it may be verified that</s></p><formula xml:id="formula_77">E v j x i (v i , v j ) = v i q i (v i ) − v v q i (t) dt.</formula><p><s>Indeed, the coefficients a 1 , a 2 and a 3 were obtained by conjecturing that x i (•, •) is linear and matching the coefficients on either side of the above equation.</s><s>The above is of course the well known necessary condition that is implied by any incentive compatible mechanism on interim payments.</s><s>It is also well known (and can be verified directly) that it is a sufficient condition for truthful reporting provided q 1 (•) and q 2 (•) are respectively increasing for v 1 α and v 2 g(α).</s><s>This clearly holds here since m α &lt; 0. 2</s></p></div><figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="fig_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>)).</s><s>As α varies over [k − v, k/2], the lower envelope of these lines describes a curve 8 C below which the project is not completed in any ex ante efficient FCE.</s><s>When α = k − v, C passes through (k − v, v) and has a slope m α = −1/2.</s><s>The tangent line 1 through this point is shown in Fig. 1.</s><s>As α increases to α = k/2, it passes through (v, k − v) with its slope decreasing continuously to m α = −2.</s><s>The tangent line at this point is shown as 2 .</s><s>Therefore the bold line depicts C in the figure below.</s><s>Observe that C remains bounded away from the line v 1</s></p></div></figDesc></figure>
<figure xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="table" xml:id="tab_0"><head></head><label></label><figDesc><div><p><s>said to be simple if there exists x such that (1) At the communication stage• Player 1 announces y only if her type is at least x.</s></p></div></figDesc><table /><note><p><s>• Player 2 announces y only if her type is at least k − x. (2) At the contribution stage, neither player makes a positive contribution unless both have previously announced y.</s><s>If both have said y then • Player 1 contributes x if her type is at least x.</s><s>• Player 2 contributes k − x if her type is at least k − x.</s></p></note></figure>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="3" xml:id="foot_0">If the inequality is strict, apply the intermediate value theorem to obtain a ( v1 , v2 ) for which it is binding.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="5" xml:id="foot_1">The reader may consult any standard text, such as Fudenberg and Tirole (1991) for details of PBE of a multistage game.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="6" xml:id="foot_2">With concave priors, however, such a uniform dominance is possible since by Proposition 6, zero contribution is the unique equilibrium outcome of the contribution game.</note>
			<note xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" place="foot" n="8" xml:id="foot_3">Formally, for each v 1 k − v, let ĝ(v 1 ) = min α∈[k−v,k/2] m α v 1 + c α . Then C = {(α, ĝ(α)): α ∈ [k − v, v]}.</note>
		</body>
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><head>Acknowledgments</head><p><s>In addition to the comments and suggestions from two referees and the associate editor, helpful conversations with Ken Binmore, V. Bhaskar, Motty Perry, Andrew Wait, Vladimir Smirnov and seminar participants at several universities have improved this paper.</s><s>We thank them.</s><s>Agastya's research is supported by Australian Research Council under research grant DP0210019.</s></p></div>
			</div>

			<div type="annex">
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><p><s>Appendix A Remark 20.</s><s>Recall that given (1), for neither player to contribute is always an equilibrium regardless of any further assumptions on the prior distributions.</s><s>We shall refer to this as 0equilibrium.</s></p><p><s>Proof of Lemma 9. Strategies at the communication stage result in one of four histories: (n, n), <ref type="bibr">(n, y), (y, n)</ref> and (y, y), the two coordinates being the respective announcements of the two players.</s><s>Following any history other than (y, y), the restriction of S(x) to the continuation game</s></p></div>			</div>
			<div type="references">

				<listBibl>

<biblStruct xml:id="b0">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Co-ordination, spillovers, and cheap talk</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Baliga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Morris</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><surname>Baliga</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">T</forename><surname>Sjostrom</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Rev. Econ. Stud</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">105</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">2</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="351" to="369" />
			<date type="published" when="2002">2002. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J. Econ. Theory</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b1">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Communication and voting with double-sided information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">V</forename><forename type="middle">P</forename><surname>Crawford</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Sobel</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Doraszelski</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Contrib. Theor. Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">50</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="1431" to="1451" />
			<date type="published" when="1982">1982. 2003</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>Econometrica</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b2">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Pre-play communication in two-person sealed-bid double auctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Farrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Gibbons</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">J</forename><surname>Farrell</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><surname>Rabin</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Fudenberg</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><surname>Matthews</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="m">Game Theory</title>
				<meeting><address><addrLine>Cambridge, MA/London</addrLine></address></meeting>
		<imprint>
			<publisher>MIT Press</publisher>
			<date type="published" when="1989-06">1989. 1996. 1990. May. 1991. 1989. June</date>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="238" to="263" />
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
	<note>J. Econ. Theory</note>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b3">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Private provision of discrete public goods with incomplete information</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">F</forename><forename type="middle">M</forename><surname>Menezes</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">P</forename><forename type="middle">K</forename><surname>Monteiro</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">A</forename><surname>Temimi</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Math. Econ</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">35</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">4</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="493" to="514" />
			<date type="published" when="2001-07">2001. July</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b4">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Optimal auctions</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">R</forename><surname>Myerson</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">Math. Operations Res</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">6</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="58" to="63" />
			<date type="published" when="1981">1981</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b5">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Bilateral trade with the sealed bid k-double auction: Existence and efficiency</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">M</forename><forename type="middle">A</forename><surname>Satterthwaite</surname></persName>
		</author>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Econ. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">48</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="107" to="133" />
			<date type="published" when="1989-06">1989. June</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

<biblStruct xml:id="b6">
	<analytic>
		<title level="a" type="main">Efficient performance in two agent bargaining</title>
		<author>
			<persName><forename type="first">S</forename><forename type="middle">R</forename><surname>Williams</surname></persName>
		</author>
	</analytic>
	<monogr>
		<title level="j">J. Econ. Theory</title>
		<imprint>
			<biblScope unit="volume">41</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>
			<biblScope unit="page" from="154" to="172" />
			<date type="published" when="1987-02">1987. February</date>
		</imprint>
	</monogr>
</biblStruct>

				</listBibl>
			</div>
		</back>
	</text>
</TEI>
